RG 079:017, State Park and Forest Commission
Connecticut State Library
State Park and Forest Commission records
1908-1967
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. State Park and Forest Commission
11 cubic feet
In 1913 the Assembly created a permanent State Park Commission charged with "supervision of all lands acquired by the state, as public reservations, for the purpose of public recreation or the preservation of natural beauty or historic association. In 1921 the name changed to the State Park and Forest Commission. The Commission now had oversight of state forests as well as parks with the authority to appoint the State Forester.
RG079_017
Multiple
Historical Note
In 1911 the General Assembly create a temporary, special State Park Commission per Public Acts chpt. 224 consisting of three members to consider the advisability of the State securing open spaces for the use of the public and to report to the next General Assembly a plan for organizing, acquiring and maintaining these open spaces. This Commission reported to the 1913 General Assembly of both the need and the possibilities of the acquisition of recreational areas.1 In 1913 the Assembly created a permanent State Park Commission per Public Acts chpt. 230 consisting of six members with the State Forester as ex-officio. The Commission was charged with "supervision of all lands acquired by the state, as public reservations, for the purpose of public recreation or the preservation of natural beauty or historic association, except such lands as may be palced by law in the charge and under the supervision of other commissions or officials. The commission also had the power to "acquire, maintain, and make available to the public open spaces for recreation, adn to act with local authorities."2
The Commission's first concern was the establishment of policies to determine the proper type of area to be included in the Connecticut State Park System. In 1914 the Commission hired its first employee, Albert M. Turner, who served as its Field Secretary. That same year the first purchase of land to provide open space for public was made consisting of five acres of salt marsh in Westport that became known as Sherwood Island State Park. Gifts played an important part of land acquisitions made by the Commission. In 1919 the Commission hired the first State Park Superintendent, Arthur V. Parker, whose responsibility was to develop and maintain the park system.3
In 1921 the name was changed to the State Park and Forest Commission per Public Acts chpt. 193. The new Commission now had the authority to appoint the State Forester.4 In 1971 the Commission was absorbed into the new Department of Environmental Protection.
See also the.
Endnotes
1Report of the State Park Commission, Hartford, Conn., 1913.
2Report of the State Park Commission, Hartford, Conn., 1914.
350th Anniversary, Connecticut State Park & Forest Commission, Hartford, Conn., 1963, 3-4
4Report of the State Park and Forest Commission to the Governor, For the Fiscal Term Ended June 30, 1922, Hartford, Conn., 1922.
Scope and Content
Includes Minutes, 1913-1947; Correspondence from E. H. Wilkins, Treasurer, 1908-1916, Albert M. Turner, Field Secretary, 1916-1941, Austin F. Hawes, State Forester, 1923-1939, and Harley F. Roberts, President of the Black Rock Forest, Inc., 1920-1928; and Reports, 1913-1967, including Biennial Reports, 1913-1934.
Arrangement
Series 1. Meeting Minutes, 1913-1965
Accession: 1996-024, 1913-1965 Accession: 1995-071, 1921-1947
Series 2. Correspondence, 1908-1940, Accession: 1995-071
Series 3. Reports, 1913-1967, Accession: 1995-071
Related Material
RG 079:016, Deptartment of Environmental Protection: Natural Resources and Outdoor Recreation
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. State Park and Forest Commission
Persons:
Wilkins, Edward H; Turner, Albert M; Hawes, Austin F. (Austin Foster), 1879-1962; Roberts, Harley F
Subjects:
Connecticut. State Park and Forest Commission -- Records and correspondence; Parks -- Connecticut; Forests and forestry -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Correspondence; Minutes; Reports
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Container List
- Series 1. Meeting Minutes, 1913-1965
  There is duplication among the two accessions listed below.
  - 1996-024
    - 1913-1942 (Box 1)
    - 1943-1958 (Box 2)
    - 1959-1965 (Box 3)
  - 1995-071
    - 1921-1943 (Box 8)
    - 1944-1947 (Box 9)
- Series 2. Correspondence, 1908-1940; 1995-071
  - E. H. Wilkins, Treasurer, 1908-1916
    - Incoming correspondence, 1908-1916; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous documents, 1909-1915 (Box 1)
    - Letters to the Legislature, 1915 (Box 1)
    - Lists of names, 1915 (Box 1)
    - Clippings about Hurd Park, 1916 (Box 1)
  - Albert M. Turner, Field Secretary, 1916-1941 (Box 1)
    Mr. Turner was the Commission's first employee.
    - Incoming and outgoing corresondence (Box 1)
      - 1916-1918, 5 folders (Box 1)
      - 1918-1921, 9 folders (Box 2)
      - 1921-1926, 11 folders (Box 3)
      - 1926-1941, 10 folders (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous documents related to the State Parks, 1918-1920 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous documents related to the State Parks, 1920-1940; 9 folders (Box 5)
    - Biographical information (Box 5)
  - Austin F. Hawes, State Forester, 1923-1939
    - Personal correspondence, 1923-1934; 6 folders (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous documents related to State Forests, 1932-1938; 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous documents related to State Forests, 1938-1941; 7 folders (Box 7)
  - Harley F. Roberts, President of the Black Rock Forest, Inc., 1920-1928
    Mr. Roberts was also headmaster of Taft Academy in Watertown, Conn.
    - Correspondence about the Black Rock State Park and Forest, 1920-1926; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Correspondence about the Black Rock State Park and Forest, 1926-1928; 3 folders (Box 8)
- Series 3. Reports, 1913-1967; 1995-071
  - W. Thayer Chase Collection
    - "All State Park Receipts and Expenditures, 1914-1942", 1943 December 31 (Box 9)
    - Park, Parkway and Recreational Study (WPA Project $3376), 2 folders (Box 9)
    - "Fire Warden Directory", 1967 (Box 9)
    - "50th Anniversary Connecticut State Park & Forest Commission", 1963 (Box 9)
  - Annual report, 1914; 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Connecticut State Park and Forest Commission; Biennial Reports 1914-1924 (Box 9)
  - Report of the Connecticut State Parks and Forests; For the Fiscal Years July 1 1926 to June 30, 1928 (Box 9)
  - Report of the Connecticut State Parks and Forests; For the Fiscal Years July 1 1928 to June 30, 1930 (Box 9)
  - Tenth Biennial Report of the Connecticut State Parks and Forests; For the Fiscal Years July 1 1930 to June 30, 1932 (Box 9)
  - Eleventh Biennial Report of the Connecticut State Parks and Forests; For the Fiscal Years July 1 1932 to June 30, 1934 (Box 9)
  - Sixteenth Biennial Report of the State Park and Forest Commission to the Governor; For the Fiscal Term Ended June 30, 1940 (Box 9)